Guide to the Shirl O. Graham Papers 1951-1976
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Shirl O. Graham Papers
1951-1976
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 343
Graham, Shirl O.
7 containers. 3.5 linear feet of shelf space. 1200 items.
Notes and correspondence, relating to research in plant pathology; also, lecture materials for graduate and undergraduate courses.
Shirl O. Graham was born in Lincoln, Nebraska in 1918 and remained there until graduating in botany from the University of Nebraska in 1941. After serving as an Army officer in the South Pacific, Graham worked with the Washington State Department of Agriculture in Olympia and Prosser from 1948 to 1950, and then entered the WSU Plant Pathology department's graduate program as a Research Assistant in 1951. On completing his doctorate in 1954, he was hired as an Assistant Professor and rose to Professor in 1968, serving in that rank until his death in 1976. Dr. Graham taught all levels of Plant Pathology courses, and conducted research in various biochemical aspects of plant diseases especially the fungus disease anthracnose, bean viruses, and fruit tree nutrition disorders. He was credited with being co-discoverer of an anti-viral antibiotic, phytoactin.
Research and laboratory notes, seminar papers, lecture notes and course materials, correspondence, and slides, concerning research and instructional activities.
The papers were arranged by topic, roughly divided between materials related to teaching and those related to research. At certain points the two areas overlap--as in graduate research seminars--in such cases the research function was considered primary, and seminar papers filed with corresponding research files. The final arrangement preserves this original order by dividing the papers into two series according to their instructional or research function.
Series I is further divided into subseries for graduate and undergraduate course materials; Series II is divided into three subseries -- numbered and named research projects, materials related to anthracnose research, and other research topics. The original titles of folders have been preserved; untitled folders have been titled in brackets according to their main subject.
This collection is open for research use.
The teaching and research files of the Professor of Plant Pathology, Shirl O. Graham, were donated to the Washington State University Libraries by the Plant Pathology Department in February, 1977 (UA 77-5).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Graham, Shirl O., 1918-1976 --Archives
Plant diseases --Study and teaching--Washington (State)--Pullman
Science; Washington (State)
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Series 1: Instructional Materials
  - Series 1.1: Undergraduate Course Materials
    - Shirl Graham (Plant Path.) [Notes on journal articles relating to P.P. 206] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [Typescript of lab manual for P.P. 106-206] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Dittoed schedules and general information re P.P. 329] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Virus and etc. [Course materials re P.P. 429, 417] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - [P.P. 429 lab technique dittos, lecture notes] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - [P.P. 429 lab technique and lecture dittos] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - [P.P. 429] Dittos. 1) Calibration of the Microscope, 2) Preparation of microscopic mounts. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Drawings and Camera Lucida [re P.P. 429] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Culture Exercise II P.P. 429 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - A Host Range Study of the Pathenogenicity of Some of Anthracnose Spp. on Foliage Plants by Ellen Walter [P.P. 429 report], Jan. 28, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Laboratory Equivalents and Standards Reference [Book] S.O. Graham Personal Copy [re P.P. 429] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - [Ms. and ditto lecture notes and handouts, P.P. 529] (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - [P.P. 529 Exam File] (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Establishing Donor Plants by Culture Cutting Lecture [re P.P. 417; article, ditto, ms. notes] (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Series 1.2: Graduate Course Materials
    - Notes for Virology Course [notes, articles, papers, corr. re development of P.P. 511] (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Plant Virology [P.P. 511 course materials] (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - [P.P. 511 Group lab reports], 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - [6 student lab report books, P.P. 511], 1966; 1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - [P.P. 511 lab exercise masters] (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Nature of Virus Infectivity [notes and masters re P.P. 511] (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Slide Series on Virus Symptoms [list] (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Origin of Plant Viruses [ditto and revision for P.P. 511] (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - [Plant Virus Serology: re P.P. 511, Fractions, No. 1], 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - [lecture and lab outline, P.P. 512] (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - [eight P.P. 515 seminar papers], 1958-1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - P.P. 535 Physiology and Genetics of Parasitism [proposal and course outline], 1969 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Amino Acids and Peptides as Dipolar Ions, Instructor's Copy (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Beutler's 1 Shop Development (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Freeze Drying (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Finagle's Laws [humorous explanation of scientific method] (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Series 2: Research Materials
  - Series 2.1: Named or Numbered Research Projects
    - [three P.P. 515 Seminar papers by Shirl Graham], 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Project 253, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Project 1448, 1959-1963 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Phytoactin Project, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Veronal Ppt. Fractionalization by Dialysis and Ion Exchange [re Phytoactin Project], 1962 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Ozette Project [w/slides], 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Arsenic Study, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Endogone Soybeans [re Project 0204], 1975 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Series 2.2: Anthracnose Related Papers
    - Colletotrichum Variability (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - [P.P. 515 paper Taxonomic Considerations of Smut Fungi Yerkes], 1951 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - [P.P. 515 paper The Species of the Genus Colletotrichum Cda, ms. Trans from German], 1957 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - CHo4 Factors on Anthracnose (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Introduction [to Strobel thesis, folder 43?] (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Physiologically Induced Morphologic and Pathogenic Variations of Some Glomerella Cingulata Isolates [WSU doctoral thesis in Plant Pathology by James W. Strobel], 1960 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Series 2.3: Other Research Papers
    - Growth Regulator Determinations (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Organelle Concept (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - [excerpted articles on host-pathogen interaction] (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Bean Mosiac Virus Material (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Cranberry Pathogen Isolates and Growth on Media (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - [excerpts and notes on viral structure] (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Germination Inducer Study (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Stock Cultures (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Media Studies--setal responses thereto (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Differential Media Study Notes and Lit. Review (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Differential Media (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Extract Additive Studies -- tables (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Temperature Studies (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Misc. Studies (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Pathogenicity and Inoculation Trials (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - [chapter outline of book on Glomerella Cingulata] (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Plant Pathology Lecture Outlines by Dr. B. H. Davis, Dept. Plant Path. Rutgers U., Jan. 1940 (Box 7, Folder 60)